A Guide to the Records of the Kiwanis Club of South Arlington, 1965-2013
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Kiwanis Club of South Arlington, 1965-2013
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 197
10 boxes.
Kiwanis Club of South Arlington
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Marr in 2012.
Historical Information
Founded in 1915, the Kiwanis Club is an international community service organization. Originally for men only, the Arlington Kiwanis started accepting women members in 1988 after the international organization voted to change the membership rules. Until World War II, activities centered on youth work, such as picnics for underprivileged children and the Boy and Girl Scouts. During the war, there was more emphasis on patriotic and civil defense activities. After the war, emphasis returned to raising money to give to local charitable groups and to youth development organizations.
The Old Dominion Kiwanis Club was organized by the Kiwanis Club of Arlington on August 21, 1947, and received its charter as the Fairlington Kiwanis Club on October 11, 1947. On August 1, 1954, the name of the club was changed to the Kiwanis Club of Old Dominion to include a portion of Alexandria, the Shirlington area, and Columbia Pike in Arlington. It became the Kiwanis Club of South Arlington (KCSA) on August 12, 1968. It is part of the 20th Division of the Capital District of Kiwanis International.
Scope and Content
This record group is comprised of files donated by John W. Marr, a longtime member of the Kiwanis Club of South Arlington, including information about the KCSA and its activities, as well as files of the 20th Division of the Capital District Kiwanis (of which KCSA is a member), and Kiwanis International. Very few of the records should be considered the "official records," although it does include copies of some official reports sent in to the Kiwanis International headquarters. It also has some historical background papers, which would be of interest to current Kiwanis members.
This collection is 3.75 linear feet and ranges between 1965 and 2013, although the bulk of the material is from the 1990s and early 2000s; there is also a good amount of material from the 1970s. The documents are financial and administrative, and only come from the donor, so there are no full runs of meeting minutes or other administrative materials. However, the collection showcases a wide range of KCSA activities, including newsletters and other publications from Kiwanis groups throughout Northern Virginia, fundraisers, and financial materials. There is also one folder of photographs. Some of the records exhibit water damage.
Record Group 197 is organized into six series. Series 1 is the files about the Kiwanis Club of South Arlington (KCSA) and has been divided into subseries: Administration, Correspondence, Finance, History, Meetings, Membership, Newsletters, and Programs. Series 2 is devoted to the 20th Division, Capital District, and includes some files about other Kiwanis Clubs in the Capital District. Series 3 has Kiwanis International files and publications, and Series 4 is comprised of files about Arlington, Virginia, including volunteer opportunities and the Inter-Service Club Council of Arlington. While some photographs are included in individual files (marked by *), additional photographs found loose make up Series 5 and artifacts make up Series 6.
Arrangement
Some of the files in RG 197 arrived at the archives with titles on them, but most were not organized. The archivist, after sorting through the collection, devised an arrangement dividing the files into the different levels of Kiwanis membership, which encompasses the first three series. The files with quotation marks (") are those named on the files received from Mr. Marr, but the dates were assigned by the archivist. Some files were subdivided by date. Most of the publications and papers were loose in the boxes and were organized into individual files by the archivist.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Researchers can look at Record Group 98: Ki-Wives of Arlington, VA, for insight into the female "wing" of the Kiwanis, which was only open to men until 1988. The main Arlington Kiwanis Club's records are found in Record Group 102: Kiwanis Club of Arlington.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Kiwanis International; Clubs.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Kiwanis Club of South Arlington (KCSA)
  - Administration
    - "Action Plan," 1998-2003 (Box 1)
    - "Administration - Club Members & Projects, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
    - "Annual Report of Club Election," 1985-1993 (Box 1)
    - "Bylaws," with amendments dated September 11, 1972 and November 1, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Major Emphasis, Report, September 1989 (Box 1)
    - Fact Sheets [n.d.] (Box 1)
    - Forms (blank) provided by Kiwanis International (Box 1)
    - "General Kiwanis, 1985-86" (Box 1)
    - General Kiwanis, 1986-87" (Box 1)
    - "Individual Efforts," blank forms to record volunteer services (Box 1)
    - "Kiwanis Club of South Arlington, 1 Oct 1978 - 30 Sep 1979 J. M."* (Box 1)
    - "Kiwanis Club of South Arlington, 1 Oct 1979 - 30 Sep 1980" (Box 1)
    - "Kiwanis Club of South Arlington Transaction Log," 9/30/75 - 5/7/87 (Box 1)
    - Kiwanis International Certificate of Election of Delegates and Alternates, May 24, 1991, June 9, 1993, April 11, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Kiwanis Invocations [n.d.] (Box 1)
    - "Kiwanis Register," October 1988 - December 1989 [Club Committee Chairman Reports] (Box 1)
    - "Kiwanis Secy 1979-80"* (Box 1)
    - "List of Committee Chairmen," 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - "Official Monthly Report," October 1970 - September 1976 (Box 1)
    - "Official Monthly Report," October 1976 - September 1982 (Box 1)
    - "Officers and Committee Chairmen," 1972-2009 [incomplete] (Box 2)
    - Officers, Committees, Budget, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Marr, John W., Notes, 1995-1998 (Box 2)
    - "Registered Agent Forms," 1999-2009 [incomplete] (Box 2)
    - "Secretary" [District Secretary's Report], 1994-95 and Club Roster, May 16, 1996 (Box 2)
    - "Special Days," [n.d.] (Box 2)
    - "Sp Program & Voucher Info 1987-88" [water damage] (Box 2)
    - "Weekly Meeting Records," 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - "Correspondence," 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 2)
    - "Marr, John W., Correspondence, 1998-2008" (Box 2)
  - Finance
    - Annual Dues Statements, 2007-2009, 2012-2013 (Box 2)
    - "Bank, 1985-86" (Box 2)
    - Bank statements and checks, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - "Banking & Savings, 1986-87" (Box 2)
    - "Budgets," 1990, 2002-2013 [incomplete] (Box 2)
    - "CC-SAK Account" [1990-91] (Box 2)
    - "Comprehensive General Liability Insurance Program," January 25, 2006 (Box 2)
    - Contributions to Arlington Groups, 1992, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
    - "General Liability Risk Management Packet, 11-1-95 to 10-31-96" (Box 3)
    - "General Liability Risk Management Packet, 11-1-96 to 10-31-97" (Box 3)
    - Income Reports, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
    - Marr, John W., Expenses and Receipts, 1991-2005 (Box 3)
    - Merchandise Orders, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - "Secretary/Treasurer's Report," 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - "Semi-Annual Billing Summary and Membership Rosters," October 1, 1971, March 31, 1993 (Box 3)
    - "Voucher File, 1983-84" (Box 3)
  - History
    - Facts you should know about Kiwanis and the Old Dominion Club of Arlington, August 1958 (Box 3)
    - "NUNC," speech [n.d.] (Box 3)
    - "Some History of the Organization and First Thirty Years of the Kiwanis Club of South Arlington, as recalled by Charter member Raleigh E. Baldwin, October 1, 1977" (Box 3)
    - A Summary of 50 Years of Service, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Meetings
    - "Agendas," 1990, 2002-2011 [incomplete] (Box 3)
    - "Official Minutes, Board of Directors," October 4, 1971 to December 4, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Official Minutes, Monthly Board Meeting of the Board of Directors, January 8, 1975, October 1, 1975, and December 5, 1978 - September 7, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Official Minutes and Treasurer's Report, January 9, 1974 to July 1, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Official Minutes of Regular Club Meeting, December 1971 to November 1974 (Box 3)
    - Official Minutes of Regular Club Meeting, October 4, 1978 to March 28, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Membership
    - "Anniversary Celebrations," 1972, 1997, 2007 (Box 3)
    - [Attendance 1980-1985] 2-36 (Box 3)
    - "Attendance," 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - "Club Committees," Instruction Sheets (Box 3)
    - "Club Members," 1979-1992 (Box 3)
    - "Hansen, Frederick T. 'Fritz'," Legion of Honor certificate, September 19, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Marr, John W., Biographical Information and Membership Certificate (Box 4)
    - Marr, Willa F., Membership Certificate, [2004] (Box 4)
    - "Membership," 1973-2003 (Box 4)
    - Membership Records, January 13, 1989 to March 1, 1996 (Box 4)
    - "Rosters," 1992-2008 [incomplete] (Box 4)
    - "Semi-Annual Membership Statment" and Membership Information Blank, October 1, 1978 to March 31, 1979 (Box 4)
    - "Smolinski, Thomas E.," Biographical information and Legion of Honor Certificate (Box 4)
  - Newsletters
    - "Club Newsletters," October 22, 1983 to December 7, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Kiwanis Club of South Arlington Newsletters, January to September 1996 (Box 4)
    - "KCSA News," November 1998-December 2002, February 2004, and January 2006 (Box 4)
    - "News and Views," 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - "SAK News," July-August 1993 (Box 4)
  - Programs
    - Adopting a Family, March 1, 2012 (Box 4)
    - "Aluminum Cans for Burned Children (ACBC)", 1990 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 1999-2003 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2004-2005 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2006 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2007 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2008 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2009 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2010 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2011 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 2012 (Box 4)
    - "Auction Benefit," 1999-2001 (Box 4)
    - Barbecue Auction, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - "Calendar Sales," 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Crystal City-South Arlington "Barbecue/Auction" Results, 1992 (Box 4)
    - 1986-2008 (Box 4)
    - Fundraising and Volunteer Appeals, November 1979 - October 1996 (Box 5)
    - The John Wettroth Memorial Scholarship Fund, 2011 (Box 5)
    - Key Club/Circle K, 1999 (Box 5)
    - "Key Club Charter - 1979-80" (Box 5)
    - Kiwanis Builders Club, November 22, 1988* (Box 5)
    - Planning for the Futuer, by Colleen Ryan Mallon and David Bonck, [n.d.] (Box 5)
    - "Program of Projects/Events," 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Serving the Children of the World [n.d.] (Box 5)
    - "Sponsored Youth" and Builders Club, 1992-2002 (Box 5)
    - WSPIDD" (Worldwide Service Project to Eradicate Iodine Deficiency Disorders), 1996-2000 (Box 5)
    - "Young Astronaut International Conference," May 31-June 3, 1991 (Box 5)
    - "Young Astronauts Program," 1989 (Box 5)
    - "Youth Services," [n.d.] (Box 5)
- 20th Division, Capital District
  - 60 Minutes of Kiwanis Education, October 1, 1998 (Box 5)
  - "Adventures of Kiwanisaurus Rex," April 2, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Bicentennial of the United States Constitutin, 1991 (Box 5)
  - "Bylaws," Capital District, August 22, 1982 and August 25, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Capital Builder, November 1998, November 1991-May 1992 (Box 5)
  - Capital Builder, June 1992 - November 1992 (Box 5)
  - Capital Builder, December 1992 - February 1993, December 1996, January 1999, February 1999, and October 2008-January 2009 (Box 5)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1979-1980 and 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1990-1991 and 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1993-1994 (Box 6)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1994-1995 and 1995-1996 (Box 6)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1996-1997 and 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Capital District, 20th Division Directory, 1998-1999 (Box 6)
  - Capital District, 1977-1982 (Box 6)
  - Capital District, Northern Virginia Regional Directory, 2005-2006 (Box 6)
  - Capital District, Northern Virginia Regional Directory, 2008-2009 (Box 6)
  - Capital District, Northern Virginia Regional Directory, 2010-2011 (Box 6)
  - Capital District Board of Trustees Meeting, February 7, 1997 1-2 (Box 6)
  - Capital District Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, April 8, 1995 and September 9, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Capital District Info, 1985-1993 (Box 6)
  - Capital District Kiwanis Foundation, Division Trustee Requirements and Duties [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - "Children's Miracle Network," 1999-2004 (Box 6)
  - "Club Progress Report," 1997-2000 (Box 6)
  - Community Service Committee [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - "Council Meeting," August 4, 2001, November 8, 2008, and May 12, 2012 (Box 6)
  - Distinguished Club Criteria [n.d] (Box 6)
  - Distinguished Member Award, 1989 and 2001 (Box 6)
  - Division Twenty, The Newsletter of Division 20 Capital District Kiwanis, September 2000 (Box 6)
  - "Interclub Report," Club Standings, 1997-2010 (Box 6)
  - K-Family at a Glance [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Key Club International, "Ten Points of a Creative Leader" (Box 6)
  - Key Leader Weekend, April 25-27, 2008 (Box 6)
  - Kiwanis Chronicles, Newsletters of Division 20 - Capital District, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
  - Kiwanis Club of Alexandria, 1999, 2004 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club of Arlington, 1999-2012 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club of Fairfax, 1999, 2010 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club of Leesburg Virginia, 2007 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club of Springfield [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club of Tysons Corner, 1999, 2008 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club of West Richmond, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club President and Secretaries, newsletter, July 8, 1999 (Box 7)
  - "Kiwanis Current," 1995 (Box 7)
  - "Kiwanis Current," 1996 (Box 7)
  - "Kiwanis Inter Club 1987-88" (Box 7)
  - "Kiwanis Kids' Fishing Day Handbook," 1999-2000 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Krossroads, Division 20 Newsletter, January 1999, April 2001, September 6, 2003, October 4, 2003, November 1, 2003 (Box 7)
  - Mount Vernon Kiwanis Club, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Northern Virginia Region, Mid-Winter Conference, March 24, 2007, March 8, 2008, February 26-28, 2010, and January 15, 2011 (Box 7)
  - Public Relations for Twentieth Division Kiwanians [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - "Scuttle Butt," September 1, 1979-March 2, 1983; March 4, 1989 (Box 7)
  - "Strategic Plan Update," August 2008 (Box 7)
  - "Teenager of the Year Award," 1991 (Box 7)
- Kiwanis International
  - "Annual Observances," [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - "BKO," Bulletin for Kiwanis Officers, October 1991, January 1992, and August/September 1992 (Box 7)
  - "Canada-United States Goodwill Week Observance" [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - Children's Programs, fliers and brochures (Box 7)
  - Club Program Development Lesson Plan, [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - Club Secretary's Guidbook, 1995-96 (Box 7)
  - Club Secretary's Guidbook, 1997-98 (Box 7)
  - "Everett Golden K Club," 1991 (Box 7)
  - The Growth Report, Analysis of Kiwanis International Membership, October 1990 (Box 7)
  - "Hugh O'Brien Youth Foundation," June 1997 (Box 7)
  - Ki-Wives Bicentennial Interclub, Program, April 23-24, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Clubs are Featuring, 1977-78, 1978-79 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis In Action, 1985, 1987-88, 1989-90, and 1992-93 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis International, Info, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis International Convention, Taipei, 2001 (Box 8)
  - Kiwanis International Foundation, 1989-90, November 1999, and June 27, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Kiwanis International Foundation, Annual Report, 1998-99 (Box 8)
  - Kiwanis International Foundation, Honors Booklet, 1996-97 (Box 8)
  - The Kiwanis Leader, August/September 1998, February/March 2002, April/May 2002, and October/November 2002 (Box 8)
  - "Kiwanis/Pepsi Program," [n.d.] (Box 8)
  - Kiwanis Public Relations Handbook, January 1989 (Box 8)
  - Kiwanis Publications, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - "Major Emphasis Program," 1988-1993 (Box 8)
  - "Manual on Membership Growth and Retention - Kiwanis International" [n.d.] (Box 8)
  - Maxmizing Kiwanis Service: Tools for Success, [n.d.] (Box 8)
  - "Membership," 1990-1992 (Box 8)
  - Membership Development Manual, [n.d.] (Box 8)
  - "Membership Roundup Information" (Box 8)
  - "Membership Roundup Information" (Box 8)
  - The Men Who Wear the K: The Story of Kiwanis, by L. A. (Larry) Hapgood, Kiwanis International, 1981 (Box 8)
  - [Order Forms] (Box 8)
  - Publications and Promotional Items (Box 8)
  - Song of Kiwanis, 1965, and Your Singing Guide [n.d.] (Box 9)
  - "Update," December 1997 - July/August 1999 [incomplete] (Box 9)
  - What Every Kiwanian Should Know about how Kiwanis Began, Member Service Department [n.d.] (Box 9)
- Arlington and Washington, DC
  - Arlington, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Arlington Public Schools, 1999-2005 Strategic Plan, September 8, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Arlington Public Schools, 1999 Graduate Survey, May 2000 (Box 9)
  - Arlington Volunteer Opportunities (Box 9)
  - Columbia Pike, 1993-1997 (Box 9)
  - Columbia Pike Revitalization Organization, 1994-1996 (Box 9)
  - "Inter-Service Club Council," 1995-1996 2-26 (Box 9)
  - Inter-Service Club Council of Arlington," 1991, 2002-2008 (Box 9)
  - [Inter-Service Club Council of Arlington, 1993] 2-46 (Box 9)
  - Inter-Service Club Council of Arlington, Annual Luncheon Programs, 1986-2007 (Box 9)
  - "Inter-Service Club Council of Arlington, Bylaws," 1990 (Box 9)
  - Spirit of Giving Guide, The Community Foundation for the National Capital Region, 2005-2006 (Box 9)
  - "Women's Committee for the Arlington Civic Symphony Orchestra," 1960-1969 (Box 9)
- Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 9)
- Artifacts
  - Letterhead and Stationery (Box 9)
- BOX 10
  - Banner and Bumper Stickers (Box 10)
  - Kiwanis International Bell (Box 10)
  - Kiwanis International Bumper Stickers (Box 10)
  - Kiwanis International Logo Stickers (Box 10)
  - Kiwanis Pin (Box 10)
  - Service Award Ribbons and Badges (Box 10)